现在，我们一直在谈论的这个虫子
Now, this bug that we've been talking about
不仅仅是迭代器中的一个bug，迭代器的版本
isn't just a bug in my iterator, version of the iterator
我们一直在谈论的。
that we've been talking about.
ArrayList提供的内置迭代器
And the built-in iterator that ArrayList provides actually
有同样的问题。
has the same problem.
for循环也会隐式地
And so does the for-loop that implicitly
使用内置迭代器。
uses that built-in iterator.
这个问题只是有一个不同的症状。
The problem just turns out to have a different symptom.
所以，如果你用这个代码--
So, if you use this code instead--
注意我们只是在使用for循环
notice we're just using a for-loop
在这里，在封面下，创建一个迭代器
here that, under the covers, is creating an iterator
在这个主题的列表上。
over this subject's list.
然后我们在同一个列表中调用一个变异器
And then we are calling a mutator on the same list
我们有迭代器。
that we have the iterator on.
那么你得到的不是一个错误的答案，
Then what you get instead of a wrong answer,
会出现并发修改异常。
you get a concurrent modification exception.
所以内置迭代器实际上
So the built-in iterator actually
检测到您正在更改其脚下的列表。
detects that you're changing the list under its feet.
当它检测到这个异常时就会抛出这个异常。
And it throws this exception when it detects that.
你可以考虑如何实施或改变
You might think about how you would implement or change
我的迭代器，所以它可以检测到。
my iterator so it would be able to detect that.
那你怎么解决这个问题呢？
So how do you fix this problem?
在这种情况下，我们如何能够删除元素
In this case, how would we be able to remove elements
当我们在这个列表上迭代的时候。
from this list while we're iterating over it.
事实证明迭代器
Well, it turns out that iterator does
除了下一个
have an additional method, in addition to next
并且有下一个内置迭代器有这个remove方法
and has next, built-in iterators have this remove method that
允许你说，我想摆脱
allow you to say, I want to get rid
在基础集合中的这个特定元素中，
of this particular element in the underlying collection,
调整迭代器的位置
and adjust the iterator's position
这样就不会出错。
so that it doesn't make errors.
这实际上也更有效，
This is actually more efficient as well,
因为迭代器已经删除了
as it turns out, because iterator remove already
知道它应该移除的元素
knows where the element it should remove
是，当主题实际移除时
is, while subject remove actually
必须搜索此主题的列表
has to search through this subject's list
以便再次找到此特定字符串。
in order to find this particular string again.
但事实上，这并不能解决整个问题，
But in fact, it doesn't fix the whole problem,
因为密码里可能还有别的地方，
because there might be, somewhere else in the code,
可能在堆栈的上面
maybe higher up on the stack in a piece of code
这就是所谓的代码。
that's calling this code.
这个列表上可能还有另一个迭代器
There might be another iterator on this very list that's
当前处于活动状态。
currently active.
迭代器将抛出一个并发的修改
And that iterator is going to throw a concurrent modification
异常，甚至可能返回
exception, or perhaps even return
一个错误的答案，因为你在这里说不出来。
a wrong answer because you weren't able to tell it here.
他们不会都知道的。
They won't all get informed.
最根本的问题是我们有多个别名
The fundamental problem again is that we have multiple aliases
在这个主题的列表中。
to this subject's list.
现在别名在迭代器中。
Now the aliases are inside iterators.
所以从根本上说，不可变的对象
So fundamentally, immutable objects
可以订立简单的合同，
can make what were simple contract,
简单的规格，突然变得非常复杂。
simple specifications, suddenly very complex.
程序多个部分中的别名
Aliases in multiple parts of your program
可能被广泛分离的依赖于物体
that may be widely separated rely on the object
保持一致。
to remain consistent.
所以合同不能只在一个地方执行
So the contracts can't be enforced in just one place
就像在一个类的客户端之间
anymore like between the client of a class
以及类的实现者。
and implementer of a class.
你现在依赖于每个人的良好行为
You now depend on the good behavior of everyone
他引用了可变对象。
who has a reference to the mutable object.
所以合同变得非常非本地的。
So contracts become very non-local.
所以让我们考虑一下Java集合类，
So let's think about the Java collections classes,
例如，通常有文件记录
for example, which are normally documented
客户的合同很清楚
with very clear contracts in the client
以及方法的实现者。
and the implementer of a method.
现在，尝试查找Java集合文档的位置
Now, try to find where Java collections documents
对客户的关键要求
the crucial requirement on a client
我们刚刚发现，你不能修改集合
that we've just discovered, that you can't modify a collection
当你在迭代的时候。
while you're iterating over it.
谁来负责？
Who takes responsibility?
是迭代器吗？
It is the iterator?
是单子吗？
Is it the list?
更广泛地说，是收藏品吗？
Is it, more broadly, collections?
尝试查看这些api并查看
Try looking through these APIs and see
你能不能找到任何关于这个的讨论。
whether you can find any discussion of this.
需要对这样的全局属性进行推理，
And the need to reason about global properties like this,
关于迭代器是否
about whether iterators, whether a list
允许在迭代器运行时进行更改，
is allowed to be changed while an iterator is running over it,
使代码更难理解
make it much harder to understand the code
并对你的程序的正确性充满信心。
and be confident in the correctness of your program.
现在我们还得这么做。
Now we still have to do that.
我们仍然需要培养这种信心。
We still have to develop that confidence.
我们仍然需要不时地使用可变对象
We still have to use mutable objects from time
为了表演和方便，
to time for performance and convenience,
但这样做的话，我们要付出很大的错误安全代价。
but we pay a big cost in bug safety when we do that.
现在这些非本地合同的另一个影响
Now another effect of these non-local contracts
是他们让我们的代码更难改变。
is that they make our code far harder to change.
因为合同比较复杂，
Because the contract is more complicated,
我们在客户之间的自由度较低
we have less freedom between the client, for each of the client
以及要改变的实施者。
and the implementer to change.
我们在前面的阅读中看到了这个例子
And we saw that example a little earlier in this reading
有日期。
with date.
换句话说，使用允许更改的对象
In other words, using objects that are allowed to change
实际上会使代码本身更难更改。
actually makes the code itself harder to change.
这里还有一个例子说明了这一点。
Here's one more example that illustrates that point.
我们例子的关键是
The crux of our example is going to be
这个方法应该查找用户名。
this method that is supposed to look up a user name.
假设是[？卑鄙小人？]在麻省理工的用户数据库中。
Let's say it's [? bitdiddle ?] in MIT'S user database.
它应该返回一个九位数的标识符。
And it's supposed to return a nine digit identifier.
九个数字作为字符数组返回。
So nine numbers that it returns as a character array.
如果它找不到那个用户，它就会抛出一个异常。
And if it can't find that user, well it throws an exception.
所以这是一个定义良好的规范
So this is a nicely defined spec that
似乎很简单也很合理。
seems to be very simple and reasonable.
现在假设我们有一个客户
Now suppose we have a client that
使用此方法打印出用户的标识符。
uses this method to print out a user's identifiers.
所以它把bitdiddle作为用户名，
So it passes bitdiddle in as the username,
返回一个九位数字，表示为字符
gets a nine digit number back, represented as a character
排列，然后打印出来。
array, and prints it.
现在客户机和实现者
And now both the client and the implementer
分别决定做出改变。
separately decide to make a change.
在这种情况下，客户担心
In this case, the client is worried
关于用户的隐私。
about the user's privacy.
在打印之前，他们决定做什么
And before printing it, what they decide to do
正在覆盖ID的前五位
is overwrite the first five digits of the ID
带星号，所以它显示的
with asterisks, so that all it's displaying
是最后四位数字。
is the last four digits.
同时，实施者担心速度
Same time, the implementer is worried about the speed
并加载到数据库中，以便实现者
and load in the database so the implementer
引入一个缓存，它可以记住
introduces a cache that remember user names that
已经查过了。
have been looked up.
所以现在当我们得到一个用户名，我们
So now when we get a username, we
看看这个缓存
will look and see whether this cache, which
是将字符串映射到这些ID的映射，
is a map that maps strings to these IDs,
不管它是否已经包含那个字符串，
whether it contains that string already,
是否有人已经查过了。
whether anybody has already looked it up before.
如果是，我们只需返回缓存的ID。
And if so, we simply return the ID that we cached.
否则，我们用通常的方式查找名称
Otherwise, we look up the name in the usual way
通过访问数据库并将其存储在缓存中
by going to the database and store it in the cache
供以后参考。
for future reference.
这两个变化造成了一个微妙的错误。
These two changes have created a subtle bug.
当客户查到bitdiddle回来的时候
When the client looks up bitdiddle and gets back
一个字符数组，现在是客户端，
a character array, now both the client,
这里的ID引用，这里的缓存，这里的映射，
both this ID reference here, and the cache, this map here,
特别是一些特殊的元素，
in particular, some particular element,
地图上有一对特别的
some particular pair in that map are pointing
到同一个字符数组。
to the same character array.
是化名的。
It's aliased.
这意味着客户的代码
That means that the client's code
会让这里变得模糊
that is going to do this obscuring here
实际上正在重写缓存中的标识符。
is actually overwriting the identifier in the cache.
所以以后再打电话给我
So future calls to get MID with bitdiddle
不会返回正确的九位数，
will not return the right nine digit number,
但是会返回这个损坏的号码
but instead will return this corrupted number
因为客户的变化。
caused by the client's change.
共享可变对象会使契约复杂化。
Sharing a mutable object complicates a contract.
如果我们
It could be very contentious if we
必须讨论客户机还是实现者
had to debate whether the client or the implementer
在这里是罪魁祸首。
was to blame here.
客户有没有义务不修改它取回的对象？
Was the client obliged not to modify the object it got back?
实现者是否有义务不抓住对象
Was the implementer obliged not to hold onto the object
它回来了？
that it returned?
我们以前没想过
Now we didn't think about this before when
我们在讨论约会的例子，
we were talking about the date example,
但现在让我们想想
but now let's think about whether we
可以澄清此规范以允许
can clarify this spec in order to allow
其中一些行为。
some of these behaviors.
或者，明确表示不应该发生。
Or, to make it clear that they shouldn't happen.
例如，我们可以说
So for example, we might say, in order
为了让实现者有自由进行缓存，
to give the implementer the freedom to do the caching,
调用方可能永远不会修改返回的数组。
that the caller may never modify the array that gets returned.
所以这将禁止来电者做这样的事情。
So this would forbid the caller from doing something like this.
他们必须复制阵列
They would have to make a copy of the array
在他们这么做之前。
before they did that.
结果发现这是个坏办法，
Turns out this is a bad way to do it,
因为这种方法的问题是
because the problem with this approach, this
意味着合同必须执行
means the contract has to be enforced
整个节目剩下的部分，
for the whole rest of the program,
对于程序的所有下游部分
for all the downstream parts of the program that are going
要使用返回的字符数组，
to use this character array that gets returned,
他们都必须有合同，
they all have to have that contract,
他们可能永远不会修改返回的数组。
they may never modify that returned array.
剩下的就只能这样了
And that has to last for the rest
节目的生命。
of the life of the program.
还有你写的其他合同
And the other contracts you wrote
范围要窄得多。
have been much narrower in scope.
你可以先考虑一下先决条件
You can think about precondition just before you
打这个电话和邮政条件
make this call and the post-condition
是你打电话后的状态，
is the state just after you make this call,
你不必为这个物体
and you don't have to reason about how that object will
在整个节目的余生中都要接受治疗。
be treated for the whole rest of the lifetime of the program.
这是一个有类似问题的规范。
Here's a spec that has a similar problem.
这是为了让客户更满意。
And this is trying to be more client-favorable.
这意味着实现者
This is saying that the implementer has
返回包含9位数字的新数组
to return a new array that contains the nine digit number
标识符。
identifier.
但是，这也不能解决问题。
But, this doesn't really fix the problem either.
它至少说阵列必须是新鲜的，
It at least says that the array has to be fresh,
但它并没有说明实现者
but it doesn't say anything about whether the implementer
可以保留新数组的别名。
can hold onto an alias to that fresh array.
它并没有保留实现者
And it doesn't keep the implementer
从更改数组或重用它
from changing that array or reusing it
在未来的某件事上。
in the future for something else.
所以这两种方法几乎不能解决任何问题
So these two approaches don't fix a problem anywhere nearly
以及使用不可变类型，如字符串。
as well as using an immutable type, like string.
因为这提供了一个保证
Because that provides a guarantee
客户机和实现者
that the client and the implementer
不能在路上互相踩
can never step on each other the way
他们可以使用字符数组。
they can with character arrays.
不依赖于程序员阅读这个规范注释
Doesn't depend on the programmer reading this spec comment very
小心并确保所有其他代码
carefully and guaranteeing that all the rest of the code
在程序中满足它。
in the program satisfies it.
字符串是不可变的，因此它提供了这些保证
String is immutable, so it provides these guarantees
是故意的。
by design.
实际上，另外，给实现者
And actually, in addition, gives the implementer
引入缓存的自由
the freedom to introduce that cache, which
可以显著提高性能。
can be a significant performance improvement.
既然这些陷阱中有那么多是不可改变的，
Now since immutable types of void so many of these pitfalls,
让我们看看一些常用的不可变
let's look at some of the commonly used immutable
输入Java API。
types in the Java API.
Java越来越趋向于不变性，
Java has been more and more been moving towards immutability,
就像许多语言一样。
as many languages have.
原始类型如int和double
The primitive types like int and double
以及这些类型的原始包装
and the primitive wrappers for those types
比如，大写I整数，大写D双精度，都是不可变的。
like, capital I Integer, capital D Double, are all immutable.
如果你需要用非常大的数字来计算，
And if you need to compute with very big numbers,
BigInteger和BigDecimal也是不可变的。
BigInteger and BigDecimal are also immutable.
现在我们看到了日期对象
Now we looked at the date object and saw
它很容易出错，但是有适当的不可变
that it was error-prone, but there are appropriate immutable
Java时代的类型，您可以也应该使用这些类型
types from Java Time that you can and should use instead
在那个变化无常的日子。
of that mutable date.
现在Java集合，比如List、Set和Map，
Now the Java collections like List, Set, and Map,
默认情况下都是可变的，因此数组列表和哈希
are all by default mutable, so array list and hash
map和HashSet等等，但是有一些实用方法
map and HashSet, so forth, but there are utility methods
这将允许您创建不可修改的视图
that will allow you to create unmodifiable views
这些可变的集合。
of these mutable collections.
所以集合点未修改的列表，
So collections dot unmodified list,
获取一个可能是可变列表的列表，
takes a list which is probably a mutable list,
把它包装成一个特殊的列表
and wraps it in a special list that does not actually
允许变异，至少不能通过这个引用。
allow mutation, at least not through this reference.
它是像append和set这样的mutator方法
It's mutator methods like append and set
等等，都抛出异常，而不是
and so forth, all throw exceptions, instead of
实际功能。
actually function.
所以你可以把它当作包装纸
So you can think of it like a wrapper
在你传递给它的底层列表周围。
around the underlying list that you pass to it.
所以如果你有一个客户引用了那个包装器
So if you have a client who has a reference to that wrapper
试图进行变异，但他们做不到。
and tries to perform mutations, they can't do it.
所以在传递可变集合之前
So before you pass a mutable collection
对于程序的另一部分，它是
to another part of a program, it's
把它包在这些东西里是个好主意
a great idea to wrap it in one of these
在不可修改的包装上。
on unmodifiable wrappers.
但在那一点上你必须小心
But you have to be careful at that point
忘记对可变集合的引用
to forget about the reference to the mutable collection
或者你会有浮动的可变部分的别名。
or you will have aliases to the mutable part floating around.
集合也有一些方法
Collections also has some methods
让您获得不可变的空集合，
that let you obtain immutable empty collections,
因为没有什么比发现你
because there's nothing worse than discovering what you
思想绝对是空的，突然
thought was definitely empty, has suddenly
由于其他部分的别名而变为非空
been made not empty because of an alias in some other part
你的计划。
of your program.